Guide to the J. B. Carrington Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
J. B. Carrington papers
1886-1934
YCAL MSS 666
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.17
(4 boxes)
The J. B. Carrington Papers hold correspondence, literary manuscripts, photographs, and research files related to his career as an editor and writer at Scribner's Magazine. Correspondents include authors and artists who contributed work to the magazine, such as Frederick S. Church, James B. Connolly, Kenyon Cox, Andrew Lang, Maxfield Parrish, Frederick Waugh, and N. C. Wyeth, who are represented by letters and literary manuscripts. In addition, Carrington kept financial records on the company's literary assets, detailing amounts paid to authors and tabulating the literary costs of each issue published between 1892 and 1906. Other correspondents in the papers relate to Carrington's research on contemporary wood engravers, including William B. Closson, Elbridge Kingsley, Gustav Kruell, Caroline Amelia Powell, and S. G. Putnam, among others. Also present are twenty-five art photographs taken by Carrington, who wrote on photography for Scribner's, and pieces of ephemera that document his activities at the Salmagundi Club.
Carrington, J. B. (James Beebee), 1860-1929
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter H. Cook (Yale 1912), 1946.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Carrington Family Papers (MS 130), Manuscripts and Archives, Sterling Memorial Library, Yale University
J. B. Carrington (1860-1929)
James Beebee Carrington was born in Columbus, Ohio, the son of United States Army General and historian Henry Beebee Carrington (Yale 1845) and his first wife Margaret Irvin Sullivant. Wabash College records show that Carrington attended that college for two years while his father was an instructor there. In 1876-1877 he was a preparatory student enrolled in the "English Course," which had no Greek or Latin, and was intended more as a business track. The next academic year, 1877-1878, he was enrolled in the first year of the "Scientific Preparatory" program, which differed from the "Classical Preparatory" program in that it offered Latin, but no Greek instruction. While he did not complete a degree, Wabash College awarded him an honorary Master of Arts in 1897.
Carrington joined the staff of Scribner's Magazine when it was founded in 1887 and remained associated with the journal through his death, both as an editor and an author of feature articles, poems, and photographic essays. An active member of the Salmagundi Club in New York, he wrote for other periodicals and lectured publicly on the topics of art and illustration. Carrington had a particular interest in the technique of wood engraving and its practitioners, and contributed the biographical notes and bibliography to Philip Hamerton's two-volume work The Art of the American Wood-engraver (Scribner's, 1894).
J. B. Carrington died at his home on Nod Hill Road in Ridgefield, Connecticut, on July 14, 1929; he was survived by his wife Eva Doolittle Carrington, who died on August 6, 1942.
Scope and Contents
The J. B. Carrington Papers hold correspondence, literary manuscripts, photographs, and research files related to his career as an editor and writer at Scribner's Magazine. Correspondents include authors and artists who contributed work to the magazine, such as Frederick S. Church, James B. Connolly, Kenyon Cox, Andrew Lang, Maxfield Parrish, Frederick Waugh, and N. C. Wyeth, who are represented in the collection by letters and literary manuscripts. In addition, Carrington kept financial records on the company's literary assets, detailing prices paid to authors for work submitted, and tabulating the literary costs of each issue published between 1892 and 1906. Other correspondents in the papers relate to Carrington's research on contemporary wood engravers, including William B. Closson, Elbridge Kingsley, Gustav Kruell, Caroline Amelia Powell, and S. G. Putnam, among others. Also present are twenty-five art photographs taken by Carrington, who wrote on photography for Scribner's Magazine, and ephemera that documents his activities at the Salmagundi Club.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1886-1934. II. Scribner's Magazine Records and Manuscripts, 1891-1919. III. Research and Writings on Wood Engraving and Engravers, 1887-1924. IV. Other Papers, 1893-1924. V. Photographs by J. B. Carrington, circa 1910.
Scribner's magazine; Magazine illustration -- 20th Century; Periodical editors -- United States; Wood-engraving, American -- 19th century; Wood-engraving, American -- 20th Century; Galley proofs -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Periodical editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Aikman, Walter M., 1857-1939; Alexander, John White, 1856-1915; Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1848-1936; Carrington, J. B. (James Beebee), 1860-1929; Chadwick, C. W. (Charles Wesley); Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1842-1924; Closson, William Baxter Palmer, 1848-1926; Connolly, James B. (James Brendan), 1868-1957; Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919; Davis, John Parker, 1832-1910; Del'Orme, Edward G. H.; Del'Orme, George; French, Frank, 1850-1933; Frost, A. B. (Arthur Burdett), 1851-1928; King, Francis Scott, 1850-1913; Kingsley, Elbridge, 1842-1918; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Koehler, S. R. (Sylvester Rosa), 1837-1900; Kruell, Gustave, 1843-1907; Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897; Parrish, Maxfield, 1870-1966; Pettit, Frederick, 1842-1864; Powell, Caroline Amelia, 1852-1934; Putnam, S. G. (Sarah Gooll), 1851-1912; Taft, Lorado, 1860-1936; Tietze, R. G. (Richard G.); Van Laer, Alexander Theobald, 1857-1920; Watson, Rosamund Marriott, 1863-1911; Waugh, Frederick Judd, 1861-1940; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892; Wolf, Henry, 1852-1916; Wyeth, N. C. (Newell Convers), 1882-1945; Yeto, Genjiro; Charles Scribner's Sons; Salmagundi Club
- Correspondence, 1886-1934; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I holds letters to Carrington from artists, authors, and others, primarily regarding their work, including that submitted to Scribner's Magazine. Prominent among them are twenty letters from Frederick S. Church decorated with his comic illustrations, nine letters from painter Maxfield Parrish, and N. C. Wyeth's autobiographical statement. One folder holds responses to a seven-question survey on the education and advancement of American artists that Carrington sent out to academics and artists.
  Some additional correspondence is filed in Series II with related literary manuscripts.
  - Aylward, W. J. (William James), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes studio portrait photograph
  - Church, Frederick S. (Frederick Stuart), 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Frost, A. B. (Arthur Burdett), 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes Frost's notes on his Harper & Brothers colleagues Samuel Stillman Conant, Theodore R. Davis, Charles Mente, Granville Perkins, and Ivan Pranishnikoff; a wash drawing of a lion, inscribed by Frost to Carrington in November 1919, is stored in Box 4, folder 106.
  - Grant, Robert, 1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hardy, Arthur Sherburne, 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hawthorne, Julian, 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Juengling, Frederick, 1888 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1897 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Leyendecker, J. C. (Joseph Christian), 1905 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Low, Will Hicok, 1919 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manship, Paul, 1916 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Parrish, Maxfield, 1897-1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Perry, Lawrence, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes snapshot photograph of Perry
  - Taft, Lorado, 1912-1921 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Watrous, Harry Willson, 1915 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Letter concerning John White Alexander
  - Waugh, Frederick Judd, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Weir, John F. (John Ferguson), 1913 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1886 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Williams, Jesse Lynch, 1906 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Wyeth, N. C. (Newell Convers), 1905-1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes a photograph of Wyeth dressed as a "cow-boy"
  - Yeto, Genjiro, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General correspondence, 1890-1934 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes letters from Adeline Adams, Henry A. Beers, Walter Camp, John Drew, William W. Ellsworth, Edgar Fawcett, Sewell Ford, Charles Dana Gibson, George C. Hazelton, Robert Herrick, Samuel Isham, Joseph L. Morton, Dudley A. Sargent, Edmund Clarence Stedman, W. B. Van Ingen, Alexander Theobald van Laer, Wabash College, and a letter from Corwin Knapp Linson to Eva Carrington (1934).
  - Christmas cards from Robert Bridges and Leigh Hunt, 1905, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Responses to survey on American art, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes replies from J. Carroll Beckwith, Edwin Howland Blashfield, Susan N. Carter, Frederick S. Church, Kenyon Cox, Jasper Francis Cropsey, Percival De Luce, Harry Fenn, R. Swain Gifford, Mary King Longfellow, Francis Davis Millet, H. Siddons Mowbray, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Rosina Emmet Sherwood, and George H. Smillie.
  - Autographs (clipped) and signed letter fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Herbert Adams, Mary Shipman Andrews, Bliss Carman (2), John Fox, W. Hamilton Gibson, George Bird Grinnell, Louise Imogen Guiney, Joseph Pennell, Howard Pyle, Arthur Ruhl, Edmund Clarence Stedman, Mariana Griswold van Rensselaer, Edith Wharton, and Kate Douglas Wiggin (2).
- Scribner's Magazine Records and Manuscripts, 1891-1919; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized into two subseries: Literary Records and Literary Manuscripts.
  The series holds Carrington's financial notes on literary assets held by Scribner's Magazine at the turn of the century, and a group of literary manuscripts that were submitted for publication. The records consist of list detailing amounts of money paid to authors, and tables of contents from issues published between 1892 and 1906, annotated with the cost of each literary work published. The literary manuscripts vary from full essays to just fragments of works, presumably kept for their autograph value.
  - Literary Records
    - Literary assets listed by author, 1890s (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Literary assets listed by year, 1892-1907 (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
    - Literary assets lists, unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
    - Literary costs per issue, 1892-1906 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - Literary Manuscripts
    - Aldrich, Thomas Bailey: "Broken Music" and "Her Dying Words," autograph manuscript, signed, and correction, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Bacon, Josephine Daskam: "The Sailor's Song," autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Bishop, William Henry: "The Last of the Fairy Wands," galley of two parts, with autograph manuscript corrections, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Blashfield, Edwin Howland: on John White Alexander, autograph manuscript, with two accompanying letters, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Cable, George Washington: "Dr. Sevier," autograph manuscript, signed, of first page; "An American Garden," fragment of typescript, signed, 1897, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Carrington, J. B.: "Magazine Notes," proof with autograph manuscript corrections, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Connolly, James B.: seven autograph manuscript poems and two typed letters, all signed, and one photograph, 1913-1919 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Manuscript for poems "The Echo o'the Morn," "From Reykjavik to Gloucester," "The Flyie Lass," "The Lucy Foster," "Masters of the Sea," "A Tommy Clancy Song,", and "The Trawler's Song"
    - Cox, Kenyon: three autograph manuscript essays and two autograph manuscript letters, signed, 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      An appreciation of John White Alexander, "The American School of Painting," and "Two Ways of Painting"
    - Harris, Joel Chandler: "The Colonel's 'Nigger Dog'," first page of autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Hawkins, Anthony Hope
    - Henderson, W. J. (William James): "Amor Triumphator," autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1897 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Hope, Anthony: "The Happiness of Stephen the Smith," autograph manuscript, signed, of first page, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Hornung, E. W.: "An Old Flame" galley page and "Raffles" typescript paragraph, both with corrections, 1901, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Krehbiel, Henry Edward: "Bayreuth Revisited," first page of autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1892 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Lampman, Archibald: "We Too Shall Sleep" and "White Pansies," autograph manuscripts, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Lang, Andrew: "Elle" and "Love's Cryptogram," autograph manuscripts, signed, with printed portrait, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Martin, Edward Sandford: "Egotism" and "Worth While," autograph manuscripts, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Page, Thomas Nelson, "Red Rock" galley of part of chapter 37, with autograph manuscript corrections, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Quiller-Couch, Arthur: autograph manuscript paragraph and galley with autograph manuscript corrections, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore: "Oliver Cromwell IV," galley pages with autograph manuscript corrections, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Sherman, Frank Dempster: three poems, autograph manuscripts, signed, and galley with corrections, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Spofford, Harriet Elizabeth Prescott: "The Wanderers," autograph manuscript, circa 1895 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Stevenson, Robert Louis: "The Wrecker," corrected proof with autograph manuscript paragraph insert, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Also includes three photographs: one portrait of Stevenson and two images of toll houses at and near St. Helena, California
    - Thomas, Edith Matilda: "City Vistas" and "The Return to Nature," autograph manuscripts, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Tomson, Graham R.
    - Van Dyke, Henry: "Pichou," galley fragments with autograph manuscript corrections, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Watson, Rosamund Marriott: three autograph manuscripts and one letter, all signed, 1894, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Research and Writings on Wood Engraving and Engravers, 1887-1924; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Organized under two subseries: Correspondence and Research Material, and Galleys and Proofs.
  Series III holds Carrington's correspondence with contemporary wood engravers, galleys, proofs, and tear sheets of his writings on the topic, and other related research files. Much of the material was gathered for his contribution to the two-volume limited-edition work The Art of the American Wood-engraver (New York: Scribner's Sons, 1894). Volume one contains an essay by Philip Gilbert Hamerton, followed by catalogue entries and biographical notes by Carrington to describe the forty wood engravings and twenty-three artists featured in volume two: Walter Aikman, George T. Andrew, C. Irving Butler, C. W. Chadwick, William B. Clossen, John P. Davis, Edward H. Del'Orme, George H. Del'Orme, Francis E. Fillebrown, Frank French, Thomas H. Heard, Thomas Johnson, Frederick Juengling, Frank S. King, Elbridge Kingsley, Frederick A. Pettit, S. G. Putnam, George A. Teel, R. G. Tietze, I. M. Van Ness, Robert Varley, William B. Witte, and Henry Wolf. Also in volume one is Carrington's bibliography on American wood engraving.
  In addition to that project, Carrington wrote a series of biographies of wood engravers for Scribner's Magazine, and the files hold proofs and galleys for those articles, as well as general research material on wood engraving.
  - Correspondence and Research Material
    - Aikman, Walter Monteith, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Andrew, George T., 1894 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Butler, C. Irving, 1894 April 24 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Castle, Frederick A. (Frederick Albert), 1894 May 7 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Chadwick, C. W. (Charles Wesley), 1894 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Closson, William Baxter Palmer, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Davis, John Parker, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Del'Orme, Edward and George, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Fillebrown, Francis E., 1894 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - French, Frank, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Heard, Thomas, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Johnson, Thomas, 1894 April 20 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - King, Francis Scott, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Kingsley, Elbridge, 1892-1895 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Koehler, S. R. (Sylvester Rosa), 1894 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Kruell, Gustave, 1889-1895 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Linton, W. J. (William James), 1889, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Miller, William, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Peckwell, Henry W., undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Pettit, Frederick A., 1894 June 11 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Powell, Caroline Amelia, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Prime, William Cowper, 1894 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Putnam, S. G. (Sarah Gooll), undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Teel, George M., 1894 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Tietze, R. G. (Richard G.), 1894 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Van Ness, I. M., undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Varley, Robert, 1894 Jun 16 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Witte, William B., undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Wolf, Henry, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Research material, 1887-1924 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Galleys and Proofs
    - Bibliography, with corrections, for The Art of the American Wood-engraver, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Biographical entries, with corrections, for The Art of the American Wood-engraver, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 94)
- Other Papers, 1893-1924; Series IV; 5
  Series V primarily holds miscellaneous personal papers related to Carrington's life. They include photographs of colleagues, a small card for his bicycle trip with the Touring Club de France which has a photograph of Carrington on the verso, a brochure advertising his availability to lecture on the topic of "American Illustration of Today," and three ephemeral items from his club, Salmagundi, in New York. Among other items is an India proof of Timothy Cole's bookplate for Flora Gardiner Kling, signed by Cole and Kling.
  - Portraits of colleagues, 1897, undated (Box 3, Folder 95-95a)
    Studio portraits and prints of Howard Chandler Christy, Juliana Horatia Ewing, Will Grefé, Philip Gilbert Hamerton, Robert Herrick, Paul René Reinicke, Frederic Remington, William Henry Shelton (2), Mark Twain, and an unidentified artist (possibly Edwin Lord Weeks).
  - Salmagundi Club dinner programs, signed by attendees, and an exhibition checklist, 1905, 1908, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    See also the photograph in Box 4, folder 105.
  - Entry form for Who's Who in New York City and State, with advertisement for lecture on American illustration, 1911, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Identity card for Touring Club de France, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1893-1915, undated (Box 3, Folder 99)
- Photographs by J. B. Carrington, circa 1910; Series V; 0.13; (1 box)
  The series holds twenty-five pictorialist photographs taken by Carrington at the turn of the twentieth century. Most of the images measure approximately 8 by 10 inches and were mounted on 11 by 13-inch sheets of heavy paper; most are not titled or captioned. Subjects include New York City street scenes including views made after a snowfall, images of sailing ships at the city's river piers, and one view in Central Park. Carrington took photographs while visiting Grand Manan Island in the Bay of Fundy, a place frequented by some of the illustrators he worked with at Scribner's Magazine; a folder of images of fishermen at work may have been taken on the island. Other subjects are cattle, a waterfall, and a portrait of Alexander Theobold van Laer and Charles M. Fairbanks sitting together in the Salmagundi clubhouse at 14 West 12th Street, New York.
  - Fishermen, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 100)
  - Grand Manan Island, New Brunswick, Canada, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 101)
  - New York, maritime scenes, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 102)
  - New York, street scenes, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 103)
  - New York, winter scenes, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 104)
  - Other images, circa 1910 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 105)
  - Wash drawing of lion at doorway, by A. B. Frost, 1919 (Box 4 Oversize, Folder 106)